I grew up in Northern Ireland, right up in the
نشئت في شمال أيرلندا، هناك في الأعلى
very, very north end of it there,
في أقصى الطرف الشمالي هناك
where it's absolutely freezing cold.
حيث الجو بارد تماما
This was me running around in the back garden mid-summer.
هذا أنا أجري في الحديقة الخلفية منتصف الصيف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I couldn't pick a career.
لم أتمكن من اختيار وظيفة
In Ireland the obvious choice is the military,
في أيرلندا الاختيار الواضح هو الجيش
but to be honest it actually kind of sucks.
ولأكون صريحا إنها في الواقع مريعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My mother wanted me to be a dentist.
أرادت أمي أن أكون طبيب أسنان
But the problem was that people kept blowing everything up.
ولكن المشكلة أن الناس كانوا يفجرون كل شيء
So I actually went to school in Belfast,
لذا ذهبت في الواقع إلى المدرسة في بيلفاست
which was where all the action happened.
حيث كانت الإثارة
And this was a pretty common sight.
وكان هذا منظرا معتادا
The school I went to was pretty boring.
المدرسة التي ذهبت إليها كانت مملة
They forced us to learn things like Latin.
أجبرونا على تعلم أمورا مثل اللاتينية
The school teachers weren't having much fun,
المدرسين لم يستمتعوا كثيرا
the sports were very dirty or very painful.
الرياضات كانت قذرة جدا أو مؤلمة جدا
So I cleverly chose rowing, which I got very good at.
فاخترت بذكاء التجديف و كنت جيدا في ذلك
And I was actually rowing for my school here
وقد كنت أجدف لمدرستي هنا
until this fateful day, and I flipped over right in front
حتى هذا اليوم المصيري، وإتقلبت أمام
of the entire school.
المدرسة كاملة
And that was the finishing post right there.
وكان ذلك هو عامود النهاية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this was extremely embarrassing.
فكان ذلك محرجا جدا
But our school at that time got a grant from the government,
ولكن مدرستنا حصلت في حينها على منحة من الحكومة
and they got an incredible computer -- the research machine 3DZ --
وحصلوا على حاسب خرافي، الحاسب البحثي 3DZ
and they left the programming manuals lying around.
و كانوا قد نسوا دليل البرمجة متروكا هناك
And so students like myself with nothing to do,
فكان الطلاب من الذين ليس لديهم ما يقومون به مثلي
we would learn how to program it.
يتعلمون كيفية برمجته
Also around this time, at home,
وفي تلك الأثناء، في المنزل
this was the computer that people were buying.
كان هذا الحاسب الذي يشترونه
It was called the Sinclair ZX80. This was a 1K computer,
كان اسمه سينكلير ZX80، كان هذا حاسب بسعة 1ك
and you'd buy your programs on cassette tape.
وكنت تشتري برامجك على شريط كاسيت
Actually I'm just going to pause for one second,
في الواقع سأتوقف للحظة
because I heard that there's a prerequisite to speak here at TED --
لأنني سمعت أنه لتحدث في تيد
you had to have a picture of yourself from the old days with big hair.
يجب أن تكون لديك صورة شخصية من الأيام الخوالي بشعر كبير
So I brought a picture with big hair.
فأحضرت صورة بشعر كبير
(Laughter).
(ضحك)
I just want to get that out of the way.
أردت الانتهاء من هذا الأمر
So after the Sinclair ZX80 came along the very cleverly named
فبعد السنكلير ZX80 جاء ما سمي بذكاء
Sinclair ZX81.
سينكلير ZX81
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And -- you see the picture at the bottom?
و -- ترون الصورة في الخلف
There's a picture of a guy doing homework with his son.
هناك صورة لرجل يساعد ابنه في الواجبات
That's what they thought they had built it for.
هذا ما ظنوا أنهم بنوه من أجله
The reality is we got the programming manual
الواقع أننا حصلنا على دليل البرمجة
and we started making games for it.
وبدأنا بصنع الألعاب
We were programming in BASIC,
كنا نبرمج بالبيسك
which is a pretty awful language for games,
وهي لغة سيئة جدا للألعاب
so we ended up learning Assembly language
فأنتها بنا المطاف إلى تعلم لغة أسمبلي
so we could really take control of the hardware.
لنتمكن من التحكم بالجهاز
This is the guy that invented it, Sir Clive Sinclair,
هذا الرجل الذي اخترعه، السير كليف سينكلير
and he's showing his machine.
وهو يعرض جهازه
You had this same thing in America,
كان لديكم نفس الأمر في أمريكا
it was called the Timex Sinclair1000.
كان اسمه تيمكس سينكلير 1000
To play a game in those days you had to have an imagination
لتلعب لعبة في تلك الأيام كنت تحتاج إلى الخيال
to believe that you were really playing "Battlestar Galactica."
لتصدق أنك بالفعل تلعب "باتل ستار جالاكتيكا"ـ
The graphics were just horrible.
كان التصوير سيئا
You had to have an even better imagination to play this game,
كنت تحتاج إلى خيال أفضل لتلعب هذه اللعبة
"Death Rider."
ديث رايدر
But of course the scientists couldn't help themselves.
ولكن بالتأكيد العلماء لم يتمالكوا أنفسهم
They started making their own video games.
فبدئوا بصنع ألعابهم
This is one of my favorite ones here, where they have rabbit breeding,
هذه أحد المفضلة لدي هنا، حيث يتكاثر الأرانب
so males choose the lucky rabbit.
حيث يختار الذكر الأنثى المحظوظة
It was around this time we went from 1K to 16K,
في تلك الفترة تقريبا تحولنا من 1ك إلى 16ك
which was quite the leap.
وقد كانت قفزة كبيرة
And if you're wondering how much 16K is,
وإذا كنت تتساءل عن حجم 16ك
this eBay logo here is 16K.
شعار إيباي هنا 16ك
And in that amount of memory someone programmed
وفي ذلك الحجم من الذاكرة برمج أحدهم
a full flight simulation program.
محاكي كامل للطيران
And that's what it looked like.
وهذا ما بدا عليه
I spent ages flying this flight simulator,
صرفت الساعات أطير بهذا المحاكي
and I honestly believed I could fly airplanes by the end of it.
وقد صدقت أنني أستطيع قيادة الطائرات بعد ذلك
Here's Clive Sinclair now launching his color computer.
هنا كليف سينكلير يطلق حاسبه الملون
He's recognized as being the father of video games in Europe.
وهو معروف بأبو الألعاب التلفزيونية في أوروبا
He's a multi-millionaire, and I think that's why he's
إنه مليونير، وأعتقد هذا هو سبب
smiling in this photograph.
ابتسامته في تلك الصورة
So I went on for the next 20 years or so
تابعت في الـ 20 عام التالية
making a lot of different games.
صنع ألعاب مختلفة
Some of the highlights were things like "The Terminator,"
بعض الرئيسية كانت مثل "تيرمينيتور"ـ
"Aladdin," the "Teenage Mutant Hero Turtles."
علاء الدين، أبطال التيرتلز"ـ
Because I was from the United Kingdom,
لأنني من المملكة المتحدة
they thought the word ninja was a little too mean for children,
ظنوا أن كلمة نينجا كانت عنيفة للأطفال
so they decided to call it hero instead.
لذا قرروا تسميتهم أبطال
I personally preferred the Spanish version,
أنا شخصيا أفضل النسخة الأسبانية
which was "Tortugas Ninja."
والتي كانت "تورتوجس نينجا"ـ
That was much better.
كان ذلك أفضل بكثير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Then the last game I did was based on trying to get the video game industry
وآخر لعبة صنعتها كانت مبنية على محاولة جعل صناعة الألعاب التلفزيونية
and Hollywood to actually work together on something --
في العمل مع هوليود للقيام فعليا بعمل مشترك
instead of licensing from each other, to actually work.
عوضا عن الترخيص من بعضهم البعض
Now, Chris did ask me to bring some statistics with me,
الآن، طلب من كريس أن أحضر بعض الإحصاءات معي
so I've done that.
فقمن بذلك
The video game industry in 2005 became a 29 billion dollar business.
صناعة الألعاب التلفزيونية في 2005 أصبحت تقدر بـ 29 بليون دولار
It grows every year.
وتنمو كل عام
Last year was the biggest year.
العام الماضي كان أكبر عام
By 2008, we're going to kick the butt of the music industry.
على 2008، سنتعدى صناعة الموسيقى
By 2010, we're going to hit 42 billion.
على 2010، سنصل إلى 42 بليون
43 percent of gamers are female.
43% من اللاعبين من الإناث
So there's a lot more female gamers than people are really aware.
إذا عدد اللاعبات أكثر من المتوقع
The average age of gamers?
متوسط عمر اللاعب
Well, obviously it's for children, right?
من الواضح أنها للأطفال، أليس كذلك؟
Well, no, actually it's 30 years old.
لا، في الواقع إنه 30 عام
And interestingly, the people who buy the most games are 37.
والغريب أن الذين يشتون أكبر عدد من الألعاب عملاهم 37
So 37 is our target audience.
إذا 37 هم الشريحة المستهدفة
All video games are violent.
جميع الألعاب التلفزيونية عنيفة
Of course the newspapers love to beat on this.
بالطبع الصحف تحب التغني بذلك
But 83 percent of games don't have any mature content whatsoever,
ولكن 83% من الألعاب لا تحتوي على أي المحتويات البالغة
so it's just not true.
فذلك غير صحيح
Online gaming statistics.
الألعاب على النت
I brought some stuff on "World of Warcraft." It's 5.5 million players.
أحضرت بعض المعلومات عن "ورلد أف واركرافت"، 5,5 مليون لاعب
It makes about 80 million bucks a month in subscriptions.
إنها تدر 80 مليون دولار شهريا من الاشتراكات
It costs 50 bucks just to install it on your computer,
إنها تكلف 50 دولار فقط لتحميلها على الجهاز
making the publisher about another 275 million.
لتعطي الناشر حوالي 275 مليون دولار
The game costs about 80 million dollars to make,
تكلفة إنتاج اللعبة حوالي 80 مليون دولار
so basically it pays for itself in about a month.
إذا فاللعبة غطت تكلفتها في حوالي شهر
A player in a game called "Project Entropia"
لاعب في لعبة "بروجكت إنتروبيا"ـ
actually bought his own island for 26,500 dollars.
اشترى جزيرته الخاصة بـ 26،500 دولار
You have to remember that this is not a real island.
عليكم أن تتذكروا هذه ليست جزيرة حقيقية
He didn't actually buy anything, just some data.
إنه لم يشتري أي شيء في الواقع
But he got great terms on it.
ولكنه حصل شروط رائعة
This purchase included mining and hunting rights,
لقد اشترى حقوق التعدين والصيد
ownership of all land on the island, and a castle
جميع الأراضي على الجزيرة، وقصر
with no furniture included.
بدون أية أمتعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This market is now estimated at over 800 million dollars annually.
هذا السوق الآن يقدر بأكثر من 800 مليون دولار سنويا
And what's interesting about it is the market was actually created
والمشوق أن هذه السوق بنيت
by the gamers themselves.
من اللاعبين أنفسهم
They found clever ways to trade items
وجدوا طرقا ذكية لمقايضة هذه القطع
and to sell their accounts to each other
ولبيع حساباتهم لبعض
so that they could make money while they were playing their games.
ليتمكنوا من تكوين دخل بينما يلعبون ألعابهم
I dove onto eBay a couple of days ago
تعمقت في إي بي منذ بضعة أيام
just to see what was gong on, typed in World of Warcraft, got 6,000 items.
فقط لأرى ما يحدث، كتبت ورلد أف وركرافت، وحدت 6,000 قطعة
I liked this one the best:
أعجبت بهذه
a level 60 Warlock with lots of epics for 174,000 dollars.
ساحر في المستوى لـ 60 مع الكثير من الملاحم بـ 174 ألف دولار
It's like that guy obviously had some pain while making it.
من الواضح أن هذا الشخص تعذب في صنعه
So as far as popularity of games,
فمن حيث شعبية هذه الألعاب
what do you think these people are doing here?
ما الذي تعتقدون أن هؤلاء القوم يفعلونه هنا؟
It turns out they're actually in Hollywood Bowl in Los Angeles
اتضح أنهم في هوليود لوس أنجلس
listening to the L.A. Philharmonic playing video game music.
يستمعون إلى إل أي فيلهارمونيك يعزف موسيقى الألعاب الإلكترونية
That's what the show looks like.
هذا ما يبدو عليه العرض
You would expect it to be cheesy, but it's not.
ستتوقعون أن يكون سخيفا، ولكنه ليس كذلك
It's very, very epic and a very beautiful concert.
إنها، إنها حفلة ملحمية وجميلة جدا
And the people that went there absolutely loved it.
وجميع من حضرها أعجب جدا بها
What do you think these people are doing?
ما الذي تعتقدون أن هؤلاء القوم يفعلونه؟
They're actually bringing their computers so they can play games
إنهم في الواقع يحضرون حاسباتهم ليتمكنوا من اللعب
against each other.
ضد بعضهم البعض
And this is happening in every city around the world.
وهذا يحدث في كل مدينة حول العالم
This is happening in your local cities too,
ويحدث في مدنكم المحلية أيضا
you're probably just not aware of it.
ولكنكم على الأغلب لا تدركون ذلك
Now, Chris told me that you had a timeline video a few years ago
الآن، كريس فال لي أنكم شاهدتم مقطع عن التاريخ منذ يضع سنوات
here just to show how video game graphics have been improving.
هنا لتطلعكم على كيف تطورت رسومات الألعاب التلفزيونية
I wanted to update that video and give you a new look at it.
أردت تحديث ذلك المقطع وإعطائكم منظور جديد
But what I want you to do is to try to understand it.
ولكن ما أريده منكم هو فهمه
We're on this curve, and the graphics are getting
نحن على هذا المنحنى، والرسومات أصبحت
so ridiculously better.
أفضل بكثير
And I'm going to show you up to maybe 2007.
سأريكم إلى 2007 تقريبا
But I want you to try and think about what games could look like
ولكنني أريدكم أن تحاولوا تخيل ما ستبدو عليه الألعاب
10 years from now.
بعد 10 سنوات
So we're going to start that video.
سنبدأ المقطع
Video: Throughout human history people have played games.
الفيديو: عبر تاريخ البشرية لعب الناس
As man's intellect and technology have evolved
مع تطور فكر وتقنية البشر
so too have the games he plays.
كذلك تطورت ألعابهم
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
David Perry: The thing again I want you to think about is,
ديفيد بيري: الأمر الذي أريدكم أن تتفكروا فيه ثانيتا هو
don't look at these graphics and think of that's the way it is.
لا تنظروا إلى هذه الرسومات وتفكروا بأن هذه هي
Think about that's where we are right now,
فكروا هذا هو ما نحن عليه الآن
and the curve that we're on means that this is going to continue
والمنحنى الذي نسلكه يعني أن هذا سيستمر
to get better.
ليتحسن
This is an example of the kind of graphics you need to be able to draw
هذا مثال على مستور الرسم الذي تستطيع أن ترسمه
if you wanted to get a job in the video game industry today.
لو أردت وظيفة في صناعة الألعاب التلفزيونية اليوم
You need to be really an incredible artist.
عليك أن تكون فنانا رائعا
And once we get enough of those guys, we're going to want
وحين نجد الكفاية من هؤلاء، سنرغب
more fantasy artists that can create places
في المزيد من الفنانين الخياليين الذي يستطيعون صنع أماكن
we've never been to before, or characters that
لم نزورها من قبل، أو شخصيات
we've just never seen before.
لم نرها من قيل
So the obvious thing for me to talk about today is graphics and audio.
إذا الموضوع الواضح لأتحدث عنه اليوم هو الرسم والصوت
But if you were to go to a game developers conference,
ولكن إذا ذهبتم إلى مؤتمر إنتاج الألعاب الإلكترونية
what they're all talking about is emotion, purpose,
ما يتحدثون عنه هو العواطف والأهداف
meaning, understanding and feeling.
المعاني، التفهم والمشاعر
You'll hear about talks like, can a video game make you cry?
ستسمع عن مواضيع مثل، هل يمكن للعبة أن تجعلك تبكي؟
And these are the kind of topics we really actually care about.
وهذه هي المواضيع التي نهتم بها حقيقتا
I came across a student who's absolutely excellent
قابلت طالبا ممتازا
at expressing himself, and this student agreed
في التعبير عن نفسه، وقد قبل هذا الطالب
that he would not show his video to anybody until
أنه لن يعرض مقطعه لأي شخص حتى
you here at TED had seen it.
ترونه وتسمعونه أنتم هنا في تيد
So I'd like to play this video.
لذا أود أن أعرض هذا المقطع
So this is a student's opinion on what his experience of games are.
هذه وجهة نظر طالب عن خبراته مع الألعاب
Video: I, like many of you, live somewhere between
الفيديو: أنا، مثل الكثير منكم، أعيش في مكان بين
reality and video games.
الواقع والألعاب التلفزيونية
Some part of me -- a true living, breathing person --
جزء مني -- شخص حقيقي يتنفس -ـ
has become programmed, electronic and virtual.
أصبح مبرمجا، إليكتروني وخيالي
The boundary of my brain that divides real from fantasy
الحاجز في عقلي بين الحقيقة والخيال
has finally begun to crumble.
بدأ أخيرا بالانهيار
I'm a video game addict and this is my story.
أنا مدمن ألعاب تلفزيونية وهذه قصتي
(Music)
(موسيقى)
In the year of my birth
في سنة مولدي
the Nintendo Entertainment System also went into development.
بدأ إنتاج جهاز نينتندو الترفيهي
I played in the backyard, learned to read,
لعبت في الحديقة وتعلمت القراءة
and even ate some of my vegetables.
وحتى أكلت بعض خضرواتي
Most of my childhood was spent playing with Legos.
معظم طفولتي كانت في اللعب بالليجو
But as was the case for most of my generation,
ولكن كما هو الحال لمعظم جيلي
I spent a lot of time in front of the TV.
أمضيت الكثير من والوقت أمام التلفاز
Mr. Rogers, Walt Disney, Nick Junior,
السيد روجر، ديزني، نك جونيور
and roughly half a million commercials have undoubtedly
وتقريبا نصف مليون لإعلان بكل تأكيد
left their mark on me.
قد تركت أثرها علي
When my parents bought my sister and I our first Nintendo,
حين اشترى والدي أول نينتندو لي ولأختي
whatever inherent addictive quality this early interactive
أي كانت الصفات الإدمانية المورثة من هذا التفاعل المبكر
electronic entertainment possessed quickly took hold of me.
مع الترفيه الإلكتروني فقد سيطرت علي سريعا
At some point something clicked.
في مرحلة ما تلاءمت
(Music)
(موسيقى)
With the combination of simple, interactive stories
بمزيج بين القصص التفاعلية البسيطة
and the warmth of the TV set, my simple 16-bit Nintendo
ودفء شاشة التلفاز، أصبح جهازي البسيط ذو الـ 16 بت
became more than just an escape.
أكثر من مجرد مهرب
It became an alternate existence, my virtual reality.
أصبح وجودا بديلا، واقعي الافتراضي
(Music)
(موسيقى)
I'm a video game addict, and it's not because of
أنا مدمن للألعاب التلفزيونية، وذلك ليس بسبب
a certain number of hours I have spent playing,
عدد ساعات معينة قضيتها ألعب
or nights I have gone without sleep to finish the next level.
أو الليالي التي أمضيتها دون النوم لإنهاء المرحلة التالية
It is because I have had life-altering experiences in virtual space,
بل لأنني كانت لي خبرة غيرت حياتي في الفضاء الافتراضي
and video games had begun to erode my own understanding
والألعاب التلفزيونية بدأت بإذابة فهمي
of what is real and what is not.
لما هو حقيقي أو ليس كذلك
I'm addicted, because even though I know I'm losing my grip on reality,
أنا مدمن، لأنني بالرغم من علمي بأنني أفقد قبضتي على الواقع
I still crave more.
لازلت أرغب في المزيد
(Music)
(موسيقى)
From an early age I learned to invest myself emotionally
منذ نعومة أظافري تعلمت أن أستثمر عواطفي
in what unfolded before me on screen.
في ما كشف لي على شاشتي
Today, after 20 years of watching TV geared to make me emotional,
اليوم، بعد 20 عام من مشاهدة تلفازا وظف لجعلي حساسا
even a decent insurance commercial can bring tears to my eyes.
حتى أن إعلان تأمين جيد قد بجعل عيني تدمع
I am just one of a new generation that is growing up.
أنا أحد جيل جديد يكبر
A generation who may experience much more meaning
جيل قد يجد معاني أكثر بكثير
through video games than they will through the real world.
من الألعاب التلفزيونية عن ما يجدونه من العالم الحقيقي
Video games are nearing an evolutionary leap,
الألعاب التلفزيونية تقترب من قفزة تطورية
a point where game worlds will look and feel just as real
نقطة تبدو عندها عوالم الألعاب حقيقية
as the films we see in theatres, or the news we watch on TV.
كالأفلام التي نراها في السينما، أو الأخبار التي نراها على التلفاز
And while my sense of free will in these virtual worlds
وبينما شعوري بحرية الاختيار في هذه العوالم الإفتراضية
may still be limited, what I do learn applies to my real life.
قد يكون محصورا، ما أتعلمه ينطبق على حياتي الحقيقية
Play enough video games and eventually you will
العب عددا كافيا من الألعاب التلفزيونية وتدريجيا
really believe you can snowboard, fly a plane,
ستصدق أنك تستطيع التزلج، قيادة طائرة
drive a nine-second quarter mile, or kill a man.
قيادة ربع ميل في تسع ثواني، أو أن تقتل رجلا
I know I can.
أنا أعلم أنني أستطيع
Unlike any pop culture phenomenon before it,
على خلاف أي ظاهرة ثقافية قبلها
video games actually allow us to become part of the machine.
الألعاب التلفزيونية تسمح لنا بأن نكون جزء من الآلة
They allow us to sublimate into the culture of interactive,
إنها تسمح لنا ننغمر في ثقافة التفاعل
downloaded, streaming, HD reality.
التحميل، التدفق، والواقع علي الدقة
We are interacting with our entertainment.
نحن نتفاعل مع ترفيهنا
I have come to expect this level of interaction.
لقد أصبحت أتوقع هذا المستوى من التفاعل
Without it, the problems faced in the real world --
بدونه، المشاكل التي أوجهها في العالم الحقيقي
poverty, war, disease and genocide -- lack the levity they should.
الفقر، الحرب، الأمراض والإبادة -- تفتقر إلى الدقة المطلوبة
Their importance blends into the sensationalized drama
أهميتها تمزج مع الدرامة المثيرة
of prime time TV.
على التلفاز
But the beauty of video games today lies not in the lifelike graphics,
ولكن جمال الألعاب التلفزيونية اليوم ليس في الرسومات المشابهة للحقيقة
the vibrating joysticks or virtual surround sound.
يد التحكم المتحركة أو الصوت المحيط
It lies in that these games are beginning to make me emotional.
إنها في أن هذه الألعاب تجعلني عاطفيا
I have fought in wars, feared for my own survival,
لقد قاتلت في حروب، خفت على نجاتي
watched my cohorts die on beaches and woods that look and feel
شاهدت الأفواج تموت على شواطئ وغابات تبدو
more real than any textbook or any news story.
أكثر واقعية من أي كتاب أو قصة إخبارية
The people who create these games are smart.
صانعوا هذه الألعاب أذكياء
They know what makes me scared, excited, panicked, proud or sad.
يعرفون ما يجعلني خائفا، مثارا، مذعورا، فخورا أو حزينا
Then they use these emotions to dimensionalize the worlds they create.
ثم يستخدمون هذه المشاعر ليضيفوا أبعادا لهذه العوالم التي يصنعونها
A well-designed video game will seamlessly
اللعبة التلفزيونية المصممة جيدا
weave the user into the fabric of the virtual experience.
ستأخذ اللاعب إلى عمق التجربة الخيالية
As one becomes more experienced
وكلما زادة خبرة الشخص
the awareness of physical control melts away.
يذوب وعيه بالواقع
I know what I want and I do it.
أعرف ما أريد وأفعله
No buttons to push, no triggers to pull, just me and the game.
دون ضغط الأزارير، دون سحب الزناد، فقط أنا واللعبة
My fate and the fate of the world around me lie inside my hands.
مصيري ومصير العالم حولي في راحة يدي
I know violent video games make my mother worry.
أعرف أن الألعاب التلفزيونية العنيفة تقلق أمي
What troubles me is not that video game violence
ليس ما يقلقني هو مدى مشابهة عنف الألعاب التلفزيونية
is becoming more and more like real life violence,
إلى العنف الحقيقي أكثر فأكثر
but that real life violence is starting to look more and more
ولكن أن العنف الحقيقي بدأ يشابه كثيرا
like a video game.
الألعاب التلفزيونية
(Music)
(موسيقى)
These are all troubles outside of myself.
هذه كلها مشاكل خارج حياتي
I, however, have a problem very close to home.
أنا، مع ذلك، لدي مشكلة
Something has happened to my brain.
لقد حدث شيء لعقلي
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Perhaps there is a single part of our brain that holds
ربما كان جزء معين في عقولنا يحمل
all of our gut instincts, the things we know to do
جميع غرائزنا، الأمور التي نعرف فعلها
before we even think.
قبل حتى أن نفكر
While some of these instincts may be innate, most are learned,
مع أن بعض هذه الغرائز قد تكون فكرية، أغلبها تكتسب
and all of them are hardwired into our brains.
وجميعها جزء من عقولنا
These instincts are essential for survival in both real and virtual worlds.
هذه الغرائز ضرورية لحياتنا في كلا العالمين الحقيقي والافتراضي
Only in recent years has the technology behind video games
فقط في الأعوام القليلة الماضية تمكنت تقنية الألعاب التلفزيونية
allowed for a true overlap in stimuli.
من السماح بالتداخل في المحفزات
As gamers we are now living by the same laws of physics
كاللاعبين نحن الآن نحيى بنفس قوانين الفيزياء
in the same cities and doing many of the same things
في نفس المدن ونقوم بنفس الأمور
we once did in real life, only virtually.
التي كنا نقوم بها في الواقع، ولكن في الخيال
Consider this --
تأملوا بهذا -ـ
my real life car has about 25,000 miles on it.
إن سيارتي الحقيقية عليها 25,000 ميل
In all my driving games, I've driven a total of 31,459 miles.
في جميع ألعاب القيادة، قمت بقيادة إجمالي 31،459 ميل
To some degree I've learned how to drive from the game.
لقد تعلمت إلى درجة ما القيادة من الألعاب
The sensory cues are very similar.
المنبهات الحسية متشابهة جدا
It's a funny feeling when you have spent more time
إنه شعور غريب حين تكون قد أمضيت وقتا أكبر
doing something on the TV than you have in real life.
للقيام بعمل على التلفاز مما أمضيته في الحقيقة
When I am driving down a road at sunset all I can think is,
حين أقود عبر طريق عند الغروب كل ما أستطيع التفكير فيه هو
this is almost as beautiful as my games are.
إن هذا يكاد أن يكون بجمال ألعابي
For my virtual worlds are perfect.
ذلك أن عوالمي الإفتراضية مثالية
More beautiful and rich than the real world around us.
أجمل وأغنى من العالم الحقيقي من حولنا
I'm not sure what the implications of my experience are,
لست متأكدا من آثار خبراتي
but the potential for using realistic video game stimuli in repetition
ولكن إحتماليات استخدام مؤثرات حقيقية للألعاب التلفزيونية بتكرار
on a vast number of loyal participants is frightening to me.
على إعداد كبيرة من المشاركين المخلصين مرعب بالنسبة لي
Today I believe Big Brother would find much more success
اليوم أؤمن أن بيج بروذر سيجد نجاحا أكبر بكثير
brainwashing the masses with video games
قي غسيل عقول الجماهير بالألعاب التلفزيونية
rather than just simply TVs.
عوضا عن مجرد التلفاز البسيط
Video games are fun, engaging, and leave your brain
الألعاب التلفزيونية ممتعة، وتترك عقلك
completely vulnerable to re-programming.
معرض تماما لإعادة البرمجة
But maybe brainwashing isn't always bad.
ولكن ربما لا يكون غسيل العقل دوما سيء
Imagine a game that teaches us to respect each other,
تخيل لعبة تعلمنا احترام بعضنا
or helps us to understand the problems we're all facing
أو تساعدنا على فهم المشاكل التي نواجهها
in the real world.
في الواقع
There is a potential to do good as well.
هناك القدرة على فعل الخير كذلك
It is critical, as these virtual worlds continue to mirror
من الضروري ما دامت هذه العوالم الإفتراضية بنسخ
the real world we live in, that game developers realize
العالم الحقيقي الذي نعيش فيه، أن يستوعب منتجو الألعاب
that they have tremendous responsibilities before them.
أن عليهم مسؤولية عظيمة
I'm not sure what the future of video games holds
لست متأكدا مما يحمله مستقبل الألعاب التلفزيونية
for our civilization.
لحضارتنا
But as virtual and real world experiences increasingly overlap
ولكن بينما تتقاطع خبرات العالمين الحقيقي والافتراضي
there is a greater and greater potential for other people
هناك احتمال أكبر وأكبر بأن يشعر آخرون
to feel the same way I do.
بنفس ما أشعر به أنا
What I have only recently come to realize
ما اتضح لي مؤخرا
is that beyond the graphics, sound, game play and emotion
أن وراء التصوير، الصوت، التفاعل والعواطف
it is the power to break down reality that is so fascinating
إنها قوة تكسير الواقع ما يبهرني
and addictive to me.
ويجعلني مدمنا
I know that I am losing my grip.
أنا أعلم أنني أفقد قبضتي
Part of me is just waiting to let go.
جزء مني ينتظر أن يستسلم
I know though, that no matter how amazing video games may become,
ألا أنني أعلم، أنه مهما أصبحت الألعاب التلفزيونية رائعة
or how flat the real world may seem to us,
أو بدا لنا العالم الحقيقي سطحيا
that we must stay aware of what our games are teaching us
أننا لا بد أن نكون واعين لما تعلمنا الألعاب
and how they leave us feeling when we finally do unplug.
وكيف تؤثر على مشاعرنا حين نتركها
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
DP: Wow.
د.ب.: واو
I found that video very, very thought provoking,
د.ب.: وجد ذلك المقطع مثيرا للأفكار
and that's why I wanted to bring it here for you guys to see.
ولذلك أردت أن أحضره هنا لترونه
And what was interesting about it is the obvious choice
ومشوق عنه هو أن الموضوع الواضح
for me to talk about was graphics and audio.
لأتحدث عنه كان الصوت والصورة
But as you heard, Michael talked about all these other elements as well.
ولكن كما سمعتم، ميكيل تحدث عن كل تلك العناصر الأخرى كذلك
Video games give an awful lot of other things too,
الألعاب التلفزيونية توفر العديد من الأمور الأخرى
and that's why people get so addicted.
وذلك سبب إدمان الناس
The most important one being fun.
أهم تلك الأسباب المرح
The name of this track is "The Magic To Come."
اسم هذا المسار "السحر القادم"ـ
Who is that going to come from?
من الذي سيئتي بهذا السحر؟
Is it going to come from the best directors in the world
هل سيئتي من أفضل مخرج في العالم
as we thought it probably would?
كما ظننا؟
I don't think so.
لا أعتقد ذلك
I think it's going to come from the children who are growing up now
أعتقد أنه سيئتي من الأطفال الذين يكبرون الآن
that aren't stuck with all of the stuff that we remember from the past.
المحررون من الأمور التي نتذكرها من الماضي
They're going to do it their way, using the tools that we've created.
سيقومون بذلك بطريقتهم، باستخدام الأدوات التي صنعناها
The same with students or highly creative people,
كذلك الأمر مع الطلاب أو المبدعين
writers and people like that.
الكتاب وأمثالهم
As far as colleges go, there's about 350 colleges around the world
ومن حيث الكليات، توجد حوالي 350 كلية حول العالم
teaching video game courses.
تدرس مواد عن الألعاب التلفزيونية
That means there's literally thousands of new ideas.
وذلك يعني أن هناك الآلاف من الأفكار
Some of the ideas are really dreadful and some of them are great.
بعض تلك الأفكار بشعة تماما والبعض رائعة
There's nothing worse than having to listen to someone
فلا يوجد أسوء من أن تضطر إلى سماع أحدهم
try and pitch you a really bad video game idea.
يحاول عرض فكرة سيئة جدا للعبة تلفزيونية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Chris Anderson: You're off, you're off. That's it.
كريس أنديرسون: اذهب، اذهب، هذا كل شيء
He's out of time.
لقد إنتها وقته
DP: I've just got a little tiny bit more if you'll indulge me.
د.ب.: لدي القليل إذا أمهلتني
CA: Go ahead. I'm going to stay right here though.
ك.أ.: تفضل. ولكنني سأبقى هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
DP: This is just a cool shot, because this is students coming to school after class.
هذه صورة جميلة، لأن هؤلاء طلاب يأتون إلى المدرسة بعد الحصص
The school is closed; they're coming back at midnight
المدرسة مغلقة، يعودون عند منتصف الليل
because they want to pitch their video game ideas.
لأنهم يرغبون بعرض أفكارهم للألعاب التلفزيونية
I'm sitting at the front of the class,
أنا أجلس في مقدمة الفصل
and they're actually pitching their ideas.
وهم يعرضون أفكارهم
So it's hard to get students to come back to class,
من الصعب إحضار الطلاب بعد الحصص
but it is possible.
ولكنه ممكن
This is my daughter, her name's Emma, she's 17 months old.
هذه ابنتي، اسمها إمما، إن عمرها 17 شهر
And I've been asking myself, what is Emma going to experience
وقد كنت أسئل نفسي، ما هي الخبرات التي
in the video game world?
ستجدها في عالم الألعاب التلفزيونية؟
And as I've shown here, we have the audience.
وكما أوضحت هنا، لدينا الجمهور
She's never going to know a world where you can't press a button
لن تعرف أبدا عالم لا تضغط فيها أزرارا
and have millions of people ready to play.
وتصل إلى ملايين الناس جاهزين للعب
You know, we have the technology.
تعلمون أن لدينا التقنية
She's never going to know a world where the graphics just aren't
لن تعرف عالما الرسومات فيه أقل من
stunning and really immersive.
مبهرة وغامرة
And as the student video showed, we can impact and move.
وكما أظهر مقطع الطالب، يمكننا التأثير والتحريك
She's never going to know a world where video games
إنها لن تعرف عالما الألعاب التلفزيونية ليست
aren't incredibly emotional and will probably make her cry.
عاطفية وعلى الأغلب ستجعلها تبكي
I just hope she likes video games.
أنا فقط أتمنى أنها ستحب الألعاب التلفزيونية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, my closing thought.
فكرتي الختامية
Games on the surface seem simple entertainment,
الألعاب على السطح تبدو كترفيه بسيط
but for those that like to look a little deeper,
ولكن لمن يحب أن يتعمق قليلا
the new paradigm of video games could open entirely new frontiers
العهد الجديد للألعاب التلفزيونية قد يفتح آفاقا جديدة تماما
to creative minds that like to think big.
للعقول المبدعة التي تحب التفكير
Where better to challenge those minds than here at TED?
فأين أجد هذه العقول في مكان أفضل من تيد؟
Thank you.
شكرا
Chris Anderson: David Perry. That was awesome.
كريس أنديرسون: ديفيد بيرري. كان ذلك رائعا